Guide to the Jerome J. Shestack papers, 1944-2011 and undated, bulk 1965-2000 RL.11610
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Subject Files, 1951-2011 and undated; Approximately 19 large boxes.
  - Countries, 1951-2008 and undated
    - Helsinki, Finland, 1979-1981, 1983-1989, undated; 3 folders (Box 53)
      Correspondence and reports regarding Human Rights in Finland, some related to the activist group Helsinki Watch
    - Honduras, 1985 (Box 53)
    - Iran, 1988 (Box 53)
    - Ireland, 1997-2000 (Box 53)
    - Israel Prisons, 1972-1974, undated; 2 folders (Box 53)
    - Israel, 1969-1973, undated; 4 folders (Box 53)
      Reports, correspondence, conference proceedings regarding human rights for Jewish people and general human rights in Israel
    - Israel, 1951-2003, undated; 12 folders (Box 54)
    - Israel, 1987-1988, undated (Box 55)
    - Italy, 1984 (Box 55)
    - Nairobi, Kenya, 1989-1994; 4 folders (Box 55)
    - Kenya, 1980-1990, undated; 2 folders (Box 55)
    - Korea, 1987 (Box 55)
    - Lebanon Hostages, 1985 (Box 55)
    - Pakistan, 2007-2008 (Box 55)
    - Moscow, Russia, 1990-1991 (Box 55)
    - Russia, 1989-1995, undated; 4 folders (Box 55)
    - Soviet Union, 1990, undated; 2 folders (Box 55)
    - South Africa, 1983-1986 (Box 55)
    - South Africa, 1984-1987, undated; 3 folders (Box 56)
    - Madrid, Spain, 1980-1981, 1983, undated (Box 56)
    - Turkey, 1980-1987, undated; 4 folders (Box 56)
      Reports and correspondence, some Helsinki Watch materials in context of Turkey
    - USSR Joint Venture, 1991; 5 folders (Box 56)
      Memos, lists, reports and correspondence regarding a collaboration between Shestack's law group and a group in the USSR.
    - USSR, 1987-1991, undated; 4 folders (Box 85)
    - Florida, United States, 1965 (Box 56)
    - United States, 1984 (Box 56)
    - Former Yugoslavia Testimonies, Interviews, 1992-1993, undated (Box 56)
  - Events and Groups, 1949-2010 and undated
    Subseries consists of materials documenting a range of conferences, symposia, seminars, awards events, and their associated organization or sponsor. Most are single folders, but larger file groups include an annual genocide convention (1949-1988), with correspondence by Warren Friedman; and an Israeli lawyers' seminar. There are many files on Jewish causes and human rights events.
    This series contains several recordings on audiocassette and video, some containing trial testimony. Listening and viewing copies must be made for access.
    Related materials can be found scattered in the other series in the collection. Arranged in alphabetical order by event or sponsor name.
    Original media are closed to use. Listening or viewing copies must be made for access. Please contact the Rubenstein Library staff before coming to use these materials.
    - American Law Institute, 1977, 1988, 2007 (Box 56)
    - American Poetry Center Symposium on Freedom and the Poet's Responsibility to Society, 1984 April 28 (Box 56)
    - American Poetry Symposium: Poetry Today, 1989 March (Box 56)
    - Amnesty International Covenants, 1978 (Box 56)
    - Amnesty International Development, 1975-1978 (Box 57)
    - Arab Lawyers' Union, 2003 (Box 57)
    - Aspen Institute, 1984, undated (Box 57)
    - Aspen Institute Seminar Binder, 1998 Nov. 13-15; 3 folders (Box 62)
    - Baha'is, 1987-1988, undated (Box 57)
    - Calendars and Planners, 1970, 1976, 1983 (Box 57)
      Calendars and planners belonging to Shestack
    - California Rural Legal Assistance, 1971 (Box 57)
    - Citizens Charter Committee, 1969 (Box 57)
    - Constitutional Revision, 1967 (Box 57)
    - Conversations from Wingspread Cassette Tapes 1 and 2, 1978 Oct. (Box 86)
      Recording of Wingspread, a meeting sponsored by the United Nations Association of the United States. Discussion between Shestack and William Wipfler moderated by Dan Price. Topics included the definition of human rights and President Carter's human rights policy.
    - Court TV Bosnia Trial VHS Tapes, 1993 April 23; 1993 May 7 (Box 86)
    - Crown Heights, 1978 (Box 85)
    - Cure Autism Now, 1998, undated (Box 57)
    - Federation of Jewish Agencies, 1980-1988 (Box 57)
    - Fortas, 1968 (Box 57)
    - Foreign Policy, 1977 (Box 57)
    - Genocide Convention, 1950-1972, undated; 7 folders (Box 57)
      Reports, brochures, correspondence and publications concerning genocide and the United States' ratification of the Genocide Convention
    - Genocide Convention, 1967-1974, undated; 4 folders (Box 58)
    - Genocide Convention Warren Friedman Correspondence, 1970, 1982, undated (Box 58)
    - Genocide Convention Research, 1949, 1970, 1981, undated (Box 58)
    - Genocide, 1970, 1982, 1985, 1988, undated; 3 folders (Box 58)
      Correspondence and photocopied publications about genocide
    - Geostratic Energy Drilling Program, 1978 (Box 58)
    - Glasnost, 1988-1989, undated; 4 folders (Box 58)
      Reports, publications, and correspondence on glasnost in the Soviet Union
    - Gratz College, 1977-1985 (Box 58)
    - Gruber Foundation, 2002-2010, undated; 3 folders (Box 58)
      Reports and correspondence concerning the Gruber Foundation philanthropy
    - Gruber Foundation Justice Prize, 2008 (Box 58)
    - Gulf War Conference, 1991 (Box 58)
      Conference proceedings and agendas
    - Gulf War Conference, 1991; 2 folders (Box 59)
    - Armand Hammer Conferences, 1979-1982, undated; 4 folders (Box 59)
      Conference proceedings and agendas from multiple Armand Hammer conferences
    - Har Zion Temple, 1980-1989 (Box 59)
    - Hebrew University, 1979-1985, undated; 2 folders (Box 59)
      Correspondence and university donation information
    - Hill Trial, 1994 (Box 59)
    - The Holocaust, 1998, undated (Box 59)
    - Hostages, 1985 (Box 59)
    - Human Rights Internet, 1981, 1988 (Box 59)
    - Independent Counsel Symposium Cassette Tape, 1998 Feb. 19 (Box 86)
    - Institute on American-Jewish Israeli Relations, 1982-1989 (Box 59)
    - Inter-American Institute of Human Rights, 1990 (Box 59)
    - International Academy of Human Rights, 1985 (Box 59)
    - International Academy of Human Rights, 1985, 1988, undated; 2 folders (Box 60)
    - International Association of Human Rights Agencies (IAHORA), 1991 (Box 60)
    - International Center of Business Studies, Moscow, 1990 (Box 60)
    - International Encounters:International Institute of Human Rights, 1985 (Box 60)
    - International Encounters: Freedom and the Rights of Man, 1985 May 30-31 (Box 60)
    - International Human Rights Law Group, 1983 (Box 85)
    - Law in India, 1997 August 26 (Box 60)
    - Lawyers Seminar Israel Workshop I, 1970-1971; 3 folders (Box 60)
      Correspondence and memorandums concerning Shestack's participation in the Lawyers Seminar Israel Workshop II
    - Lawyers Seminar Israel Workshop II, 1971-1972 (Box 60)
      Correspondence and memorandums concerning Shestack's participation in the Lawyers Seminar Israel Workshop I
    - Lawyers Seminar Israel, 1970-1973, undated; 5 folders (Box 85)
      Reports, correspondence, and memoranda regarding the Lawyer's Seminar in Israel
    - Lists, 1971-1978, undated; 5 folders (Box 60)
      Organizational Membership Lists, Personal Lists of Names and Addresses
    - Madrid Hammer Conference, 1984 (Box 60)
    - Madrid Hammer Conference Photo Book, 1984 Dec. (Box 62)
      Photos of attendees and speakers at the 1984 Armand Hammer Conference in Madrid.
    - McGill Conference, 1974 April 21-23 (Box 60)
    - Militia, 1995 (Box 60)
    - Mondale's Israel Visit, 1978 (Box 60)
    - Mondale Luncheon, 1983 (Box 61)
    - National Judicial College Panel Files, 1999 Feb. 15; 5 folders (Box 63)
      Binder files from a panel on the Independence of the Judiciary. Shestack was a panelist.
    - NBC, 1976 (Box 85)
    - NGOs, 1984, 1987 Jan., undated; 3 folders (Box 61)
      NGO directories, and the United Nations Office of Public Information guide
    - Paris Conference, 1985; 2 folders (Box 61)
    - Philadelphia Bar Association Sitting Judges, 1962, 1969-1971; 4 folders (Box 61)
      Correspondence, election materials, and political reports concerning the Philadelphia Bar Association Sitting Judges
    - Portugal Interreligion Conference, 1977 (Box 61)
    - Pro Bono Work, 1981-1985, 2001 (Box 61)
    - Scrapbook Materials, 1959, 1977, 1984, 1986, undated; 2 folders (Box 61)
      Materials put aside for a scrapbook to document Shestack's human rights work at specific events and activist groups.
    - South African Law Conference, 1995-1996 (Box 61)
    - Soviet Jews, 1980-1982, undated (Box 61)
    - Soviet Law, 1989 (Box 61)
    - Soviet Representation, 1990-1991 (Box 61)
    - Soviet Seminar, 1990 (Box 62)
    - Spanish Association, 1984 (Box 62)
    - Torture, 1987 (Box 62)
    - Uppsala Conference, 1972; 2 folders (Box 62)
      Conference materials discuss the Freedom of Movement and the Uppsala Declaration
    - Uppsala, 1984 (Box 62)
      Correspondence concerning Uppsala
    - UNESCO Human Rights Manual, 1995, 2002 (Box 62)
    - UNESCO, 1978, 1980, 1983 (Box 62)
    - US Commission Chicago Hearing, 1993 April 16; 2 folders (Box 62)
      Binder files from the US Commission on Improving the Effectiveness of the UN Chicago Hearing
    - US Commission Los Angeles Hearing, 1993 February 1; 2 folders (Box 62)
      Binder files from the US Commission on Improving the Effectiveness of the UN Los Angeles Hearing
    - University of Pennsylvania, 1981-1982 (Box 62)
    - War Crimes Conference, 1991, undated (Box 62)
    - Wingspread, 1984, undated (Box 62)
    - Yuridicheskaya Literatura, 1990 (Box 62)
  - Personal Binder Files, 1963-2006 and undated
    Subseries consists of materials of personal nature that Shestack originally stored in several binders. Files include biographical materials as well as materials that Shestack kept for personal research. These files also include some photos from Shestack's later career.
    - Eleanor Roosevelt Research Binder Files, 1983, 1988, undated; 4 folders (Box 63)
      Articles and reports that Shestack used for his research on Eleanor Roosevelt.
    - Biographical Materials Binder Files, 1973-1980 (Box 63)
      Contains materials collected by Shestack of personal value such as published profiles of Shestack, personal letters, interview files for a biographical documentary, and awarded certificates
    - Biographical Materials Binder Files, 1994-2006, undated; 3 folders (Box 85)
    - Personal Photos, 1974, 1979, 1985, undated (Box 85)
    - Awards and Certificates, 1976, 1978 (Box 85)
    - Personal Publications, 1966, 1979 (Box 85)
      Includes MacBird by Barbara Garson and Chameleon: Poems translated from Hebrew by Raquel Chalfi
    - Research Binder Files, 1963-1982, undated; 5 folders (Box 63)
      Files include articles, some correspondence, memorandums, and pamphlets collected in binders by Shestack for personal use. Materials are related to Human Rights and legal subjects and activities.
  - Other Materials, 1960-2011 and undated
    The Other Materials subseries contains loose, unfiled documents found throughout Shestack's original collection of files. The documents were placed into files and arranged by decade. Materials include correspondence, memoranda, and other documents related to Shestack's professional work.
    - Loose Papers, 1960-1969 (Box 63)
      Various loose documents arranged by decade. Most concern human rights and legal matters. Some documents retrieved from Shestack's personal desk.
    - Loose Papers, 1970-1979 (Box 63)
    - Loose Papers, 1970-1979; 9 folders (Box 64)
    - Loose Papers, 1980-1989; 4 folders (Box 64)
    - Loose Papers, 1980-1989; 8 folders (Box 65)
    - Loose Papers, 1990-1999; 5 folders (Box 65)
    - Loose Papers, 1990-1999; 4 folders (Box 66)
    - Loose Papers, 2000-2011 (Box 66)
    - Loose Papers, undated; 11 folders (Box 66)
    - Loose Papers, undated; 3 folders (Box 67)
- Writings and Speeches, 1944-2010 and undated
  This series consists of essays, speeches, articles, and book reviews written by Shestack over the course of his life and professional career. Most materials are related to legal and human rights work, but some personal writing is included as well, including eulogies, personal introductions, Shestack's World War II diary, and his autobiographical memoir.
  Some draft copies of various writings are found throughout the series. Other writings are typed copies of materials written at an earlier date.
  Related materials may be found in the Writings subseries of the American Bar Association series and throughout the Organizations series.
  - Chronological, 1946, 1960-2010 and undated
    This subseries contains writings and speeches by Shestack on various human rights and legal topics. Arranged by decade.
    - Chronological Writings and Speeches, 1946, 1960-1969 (Box 67)
      Writings and speeches by Shestack written over the course of his career. Includes remarks on the law profession, human rights issues, keynote introductions, and eulogies.
    - Chronological Writings and Speeches, 1970-1979; 5 folders (Box 67)
    - Chronological Writings and Speeches, 1980-1989; 7 folders (Box 67)
    - Chronological Writings and Speeches, 1980-1989; 2 folders (Box 68)
    - Chronological Writings and Speeches, 1990-1999; 9 folders (Box 68)
    - Chronological Writings and Speeches, 2000-2010; 3 folders (Box 68)
    - Chronological Writings and Speeches, 2000-2010; 4 folders (Box 69)
    - Chronological Writings and Speeches, undated; 7 folders (Box 69)
  - By Subject, 1944-1946, 1961-2008 and undated
    Materials in this subseries include speeches, writings, articles, and book reviews written throughout Shestack's career, as well as his autobiographical memoir and a World War II diary. Materials also include materials from a seminar series for new legal professionals written and provided by Shestack. Arranged alphabetically.
    Related written articles by Shestack may also be found in the Clippings subseries of Print Materials.
    - Baldwin Memorial Speech Material, 1982 (Box 69)
    - The Philosophy of Human Rights Materials, 1980-1982, undated; 2 folders (Box 69)
    - Human Rights, The National Interest and U.S. Foreign Policy Speech Materials, 1989 (Box 69)
    - Reform Speech Materials, 1984, 1986, undated (Box 69)
    - Remembering When: A Memoir 1923-1946, undated (Box 69)
      Autobiographical memoir of Shestack's childhood, typed and bound at a later date
    - Shestack Seminar Materials, 2007, 2008; 2 folders (Box 70)
      Writings and lesson materials from a seminar series that Shestack created for professionals entering the legal field
    - World War II Diary, 1944-1946 (Box 70)
      Diary from Shestack's time in the military during World War II, typed and bound at a later date.
    - Newspaper Articles and Opinion Editorials, 1973-2000, undated (Box 70)
      Photocopied articles written by Shestack as well as accompanying letters he sent to newspapers to request article publication
    - Book Reviews, 1961-1993, undated (Box 70)
  - Speech Binder Files, 1963-2009 and undated
    Subseries contains speech indexes kept by Shestack, and drafts of speeches by Shestack pertaining to various human rights and legal subjects. Files were originally bound in plastic binders. Loosely arranged in chronological order.
    - Writing and Speech Indexes, 2009, undated; 3 folders (Box 70)
    - Insurance Binder Materials, 1968-1969 (Box 70)
      Bound speeches to insurance agents as part of Supreme Court work
    - International Law and World Peace Through Law Binder Materials, 1963-1969 (Box 70)
      Bound writings and speeches on International Law and World Peace Through Law
    - Introduction Binder Materials, 1963-1973 (Box 70)
      Introductions of colleagues by Shestack.
    - Supreme Court Binder Materials, 1964-1968 (Box 70)
      Writings and speeches regarding the Supreme Court
    - General Speech and Article Binder Materials, 1972-1992; 5 folders (Box 70)
      Various speeches bound with table of contents
    - General Speech and Article Binder Materials, 1980-2007, undated; 11 folders (Box 71)
  - By Others, 1968, 1977, 1982, undated
    Files house writings and speeches collected by Shestack that were written by friends and professional colleagues. Topics include human rights, legal work, and some are about Shestack.
    - Writings and Speeches by Others, 1968, 1977, 1982, undated; 3 folders (Box 71)
      Collected writings and speeches given by other people
- Print Materials, 1948-2009 and undated; 9 large boxes
  Series consists of various printed publications collected by Shestack for professional and personal purposes. Most materials are from organizations of which Shestack was a member or on various subjects regarding human rights or the legal profession. Formats include serials, journals, reprints, reports, pamphlets and brochures, clippings of articles, and books collected by Shestack. Essays on Human Rights: Contemporary Issues and Jewish Perspectives, co-edited by Shestack, is also included.
  Many other print materials can be found in the files of the American Bar Association and Organizations series. Published writings by Shestak are in the Writings and Speeches series.
  - Serials, Journals, and Reports, 1948-2009 and undated
    The materials in this subseries consist of a variety of serials, journals, and reports related to Shestack's legal work as well as his participation in various human rights organizations.
    - Serials, 1973-1998, undated; 4 folders (Box 71)
      Including but not limited to: Human Rights Watch, Marketing for Lawyers, Chronicle of Human Rights in the USSR, IRR's human rights, The Shingle, Lawyer's Committee Bulletin, Commonquest, Judicature
    - Serials, 1954-1999; 14 folders (Box 72)
    - Serials, 1970-1999; 3 folders (Box 73)
    - Journals, 1948-2000, undated; 8 folders (Box 73)
      Includes various law school journals and reprints
    - Reports, 1967-2001, undated; 13 folders (Box 74)
      Including but not limited to state bar reports, Americas Watch reports, Helsinki Watch reports, conference reports, NGO reports, and country-based reports on human rights issues.
    - Reports, 1952-2007, undated; 13 folders (Box 75)
    - Reports, 1965-2001, undated; 9 folders (Box 76)
  - Pamphlets, 1972-1999 and undated
    This subseries consists of brochures and pamphlets that Shestack collected from a variety of human rights organizations and events that he attended.
    - Pamphlets, 1972-1999, undated; 2 folders (Box 76)
      Includes pamphlets for galas, organization information, and human rights topics
    - Pamphlets, 1980, 1988, undated (Box 77)
  - Clippings, 1969-2009 and undated
    This subseries contains clippings from various newspapers and other print publications related to Shestack's professional work. Most clippings of articles are written by others, though a few are written by Shestack himself, including many opinion editorials. Many clippings are photocopies. Files are loosely arranged in chronological order.
    - Clippings, 1969-2009, undated; 18 folders (Box 77)
      Clippings from various newspapers and print sources including but not limited to the Legal Intelligencer, Philadelphia Inquirer, and the Washington Post
    - Clippings, 1960-2007; 19 folders (Box 78)
    - Clippings, 1970-2007 and undated; 11 folders (Box 79)
  - Books, 1969, 1979, undated
    The subseries contains books owned by Shestack including For Men in a Free World: A Survey of Human Rights in the US, a few booklet publications relating to Judaism and Jewish History, and Essays on Human Rights: Contemporary Issues and Jewish Perspectives, of which Shestack was a co-editor.
    - Essays on Human Rights: Contemporary Issues and Jewish Perspectives, 1979 May (Box 79)
      Collection of essays edited by David Sidorsky in collaboration with Sidney Liskofsky and Jerome Shestack
    - For Men in a Free World: A Survey of Human Rights in the US, 1969 July (Box 79)
    - Publications relating to Judaism and Jewish History, 1979, undated (Box 79)
      Includes Anne Frank: A Play by Meyer Levin; Landscapes of Jewish History art brochure by Samuel Bak; and the Program for the Harvard University Center for Jewish Studies.